<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section id="actions-database">
    <title>Connecting to the database</title>
  
    <para>In many cases it is necessary to access the database during a test. This enables a tester to also validate 
    the persistent data in a database. It might also be helpful to prepare the database with some test data before running a test. 
    You can do this using the two database actions that are descirbed in the following sections.</para>
    
    <section id="actions-database-update">
      <title>Updating the database</title>
  
      <para>The &lt;sql&gt; action simply executes a group of SQL statements in order to change data in a database.
      Typically the action is used to prepare the database at the beginning of a test or to clean up the
      database at the end of a test. You can specify SQL statements like INSERT, UPDATE,
      DELETE, CREATE TABLE, ALTER TABLE and many more.</para>
      
      <para>On the one hand you can specify the statements as inline SQL or stored in an external
      SQL resource file as shown in the next two examples.</para>
      
      <programlisting>
  &lt;actions&gt;
      &lt;sql datasource=&quot;someDataSource&quot;&gt;
          &lt;statement&gt;DELETE FROM CUSTOMERS&lt;/statement&gt;
          &lt;statement&gt;DELETE FROM ORDERS&lt;/statement&gt;
      &lt;/sql&gt;
      
      &lt;sql datasource=&quot;myDataSource&quot;&gt;
          &lt;resource file=&quot;file:tests/unit/resources/script.sql&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;/sql&gt;
  &lt;/actions&gt;
      </programlisting>
      
      <para>The first action uses inline SQL statements defined directly inside the test case. The next action uses an external 
      SQL resource file instead. The file resource can hold several SQL statements separated by new lines. All statements inside 
      the file are executed sequentially by the framework.</para>
      
      <important>
        <para>You have to pay attention to some rules when dealing with external SQL resources.</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
          <listitem>
              <para>Each statement should begin in a new line</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
              <para>It is not allowed to define statements with word wrapping</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
              <para>Comments begin with two dashes &quot;--&quot;</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </important>
      
      <note>
        <para>The external file is referenced either as file system resource or class path resource,
        by using the &quot;file:&quot; or &quot;classpath:&quot; prefix.</para>
      </note>
      
      <para>Both examples use the &quot;datasource&quot; attribute. This value defines the database data source to be used. The connection to
      a data source is mandatory, because the test case does not know about user credentials or database names. The 'datasource' attribute 
      references predefined data sources that are located in a separate Spring configuration file.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="actions-database-query">
      <title>Verifying data from the database</title>
      
      <para>The &lt;sql&gt; action is specially designed to execute SQL queries (SELECT * FROM). So the test is able to get data from a database. 
      The query results are validated against expected data as shown in the next example.</para>
      
      <programlisting>
  &lt;sql datasource=&quot;testDataSource&quot;&gt;
      &lt;statement&gt;select NAME from CUSTOMERS where ID='${customerId}'&lt;/statement&gt;
      &lt;statement&gt;select count(*) from ERRORS&lt;/statement&gt;
      &lt;statement&gt;select ID from ORDERS where DESC LIKE 'Def%'&lt;/statement&gt;
      &lt;statement&gt;select DESCRIPTION from ORDERS where ID='${id}'&lt;/statement&gt;
      
      &lt;validate column=&quot;ID&quot; value=&quot;1&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;validate column=&quot;NAME&quot; value=&quot;Deppisch&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;validate column=&quot;COUNT(*)&quot; value=&quot;${rowsCount}&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;validate column=&quot;DESCRIPTION&quot; value=&quot;null&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;/sql&gt;
      </programlisting>
      
      <para>The action &lt;sql&gt; offers a wide range of validating functionality for database result sets. First
      of all you have to select the data via SQL statements. Here again you have the choice to use inline SQL
      statements or external file resource pattern.</para>
      
      <para>The result sets are validated through &lt;validate&gt; elements. It is possible to do a detailed check on
      every selected column of the result set. Simply refer to the selected column name in order to validate its
      value. The usage of test variables is supported as well as database expressions like count(), avg(), min(),
      max().</para>
      
      <para>You simply define the &lt;validate&gt; entry with the column name as the &quot;column&quot; attribute and any expected
      value expression as expected &quot;value&quot;. The framework then will check the column to fit the expected value and raise 
      validation errors in case of mismatch.</para>
      
      <para>Looking at the first SELECT statement in the example you will see that test variables are supported in the 
      SQL statements. The framework will replace the variable with its respective value before sending it to the database.</para>
      
      <para>In the validation section variables can be used too. Look at the third validation entry, where the variable
      &quot;${rowsCount}&quot; is used. The last validation in this example shows, that <literal>NULL</literal> values are 
      also supported as expected values.</para>
      
      <para>If a single validation happens to fail, the whole action will fail with respective validation errors.</para>
      
      <note>
        <para>When validating database query result sets Citrus can only handle single </para>
      </note>
    </section>
</section>