<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section id="actions-purge">
    <title>Purging JMS destinations</title>

    <para>Purging JMS destinations during the test run is quite essential. Different test cases can influence each other when sending
    messages to the same JMS destinations. A test case should only receive those messages that actually belong to it. Therefore it is a 
    good idea to purge all JMS queue destinations between the test cases. Obsolete messages that are stuck in a JMS queue for some 
    reason are then removed so that the following test case is not offended.</para>
    
    <para>So we need to purge some JMS queues in out test case. This can be done with following action definition:</para>
    
    <programlisting>
  &lt;testcase name=&quot;purgeTest&quot;&gt;
    &lt;actions&gt;
        &lt;purge-jms-queues&gt;
            &lt;queue name=&quot;Some.JMS.QUEUE.Name&quot;/&gt;
            &lt;queue name=&quot;Another.JMS.QUEUE.Name&quot;/&gt;
            &lt;queue name=&quot;My.JMS.QUEUE.Name&quot;/&gt;
        &lt;/purge-jms-queues&gt;
        
        &lt;purge-jms-queues connection-factory=&quot;connectionFactory&quot;&gt;
            &lt;queue name=&quot;Some.JMS.QUEUE.Name&quot;/&gt;
            &lt;queue name=&quot;Another.JMS.QUEUE.Name&quot;/&gt;
            &lt;queue name=&quot;My.JMS.QUEUE.Name&quot;/&gt;
        &lt;/purge-jms-queues&gt;
    &lt;/actions&gt;
  &lt;/testcase&gt;
    </programlisting>
    
    <para>Purging the JMS queues in every test case is quite exhausting because every test case needs to define a purging action at the 
    very beginning of the test. Fortunately the test suite definition offers tasks to run before, between and after the test cases which 
    should ease up this tasks a lot. The test suite offers a very simple way to purge the destinations between the tests. 
    See <xref linkend="testsuite-tasks"/> for more information about this.</para>
        
    <para>When using the special tasks between a test case you might define a normal Spring bean definition that is referenced then. The 
    'com.consol.citrus.actions.PurgeJmsQueuesAction' action offers the property "queueNames" to hold all destination names 
    that are supposed to be purged. As you can see in the next example it is quite easy to specify a group of destinations in the Spring configuration.
    This purging bean is then added to the test suite in the tasks between section.</para>
        
    <programlisting>
  &lt;bean id=&quot;purgeJmsQueues&quot;
      class=&quot;com.consol.citrus.actions.PurgeJmsQueuesAction&quot;&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;connectionFactory&quot;&gt;
          &lt;ref bean=&quot;tibcoQueueConnectionFactory&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;/property&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;queueNames&quot;&gt;
          &lt;list&gt;
              &lt;value&gt;${jms.queue.hello.request.in}&lt;/value&gt;
              &lt;value&gt;${jms.queue.hello.response.out}&lt;/value&gt;
              &lt;value&gt;${jms.queue.echo.request}&lt;/value&gt;
              &lt;value&gt;${jms.queue.echo.response}&lt;/value&gt;
              &lt;value&gt;JMS.Queue.Dummy&lt;/value&gt;
          &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;
    </programlisting>
    
</section>