<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section id="containers-iterate">
    <title>Iterate</title>

    <para>Iterations are very powerful elements when describing complex logic. The container executes the embedded actions 
    several times. The container will continue with looping as long as the defined breaking condition string evaluates to 
    <literal>true</literal>. In case the condition evaluates to <literal>false</literal> the iteration will break an finish execution.</para>
    
    <programlisting>
  &lt;testcase name=&quot;iterateTest&quot;&gt;
      &lt;actions&gt;
          &lt;iterate index=&quot;i&quot; 
                      condition=&quot;i lt 5&quot;&gt;
              &lt;echo&gt;
                  &lt;message&gt;index is: ${i}&lt;/message&gt;
              &lt;/echo&gt;
          &lt;/iterate&gt;
      &lt;/actions&gt;
  &lt;/testcase&gt;
    </programlisting>
    
    <para>The attribute &quot;index&quot; automatically defines a new variable that holds the actual loop index 
    starting at &quot;1&quot;. This index variable is available as a normal variable inside the iterate container. Therefore it is possible
    to print out the actual loop index in the echo action as shown in the above example.</para>

    <para>The condition string is mandatory and describes the actual end of the loop. In iterate containers the loop
    will break in case the condition evaluates to <literal>false</literal>.</para>
    
    <para>The condition string can be any Boolean expression and supports several operators:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
        <listitem>
            <para>lt (lower than)</para>
        </listitem>    
        <listitem>
            <para>lt= (lower than equals)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>gt (greater than)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>gt= (greater than equals)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>= (equals)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>and (logical combining of two Boolean values)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>or (logical combining of two Boolean values)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>() (brackets)</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <important>
      <para>It is very important to notice that the condition is evaluated before the very first iteration takes place. 
      The loop therefore can be executed 0-n times according to the condition value.</para>
    </important>
    
</section>