<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface id="preface">
  <title>Preface</title>

  <para>Integration testing can be very hard, especially when there are no sufficient tools that support you. Regarding Java 
  unit testing very good tools and APIs exists (JUnit, TestNG, EasyMock, and many more). The testing tools support you and 
  try to ease up your life as a tester who is in charge of testing a software in various ways.
   
  When speaking of integration testing in a service-oriented architecture (SOA) things are getting evil. Besides unit testing efforts
  especially those Enterprise Application Integration (EAI) projects need to be tested regarding their integration into the existing application 
  environment on the customer side. Without sufficient tool support the integration testing is exhausting and sometimes barely possible.</para> 
  
  <para>Testing can then be a hard task, because the tester may be forced to simulate several external interface applications. 
  The simulation of interface partners cause severe problems regarding maintainability and interoperability. It is not unusual, 
  that a tester has to simulate several applications manually during a test, because of lacking tool support. This manual test approach is 
  very time consuming and error prone. Every time a tester has to manually validate the success of at test case it is difficult to
  repeat those tests every time a change was made in the source code of the application. Regression testing and continuous testing is very important
  but not possible the time testers are forced to manually test the applications. Fully automated integration testing of whole use cases in an end-to-end
  point of view is very difficult using this manual testing approach.</para>
  
  <para>The Citrus test framework aims to fill in this gap. The tool helps you to perform complex integration testing in a message based 
  EAI environment. Citrus is designed to completely test whole use case scenarios in an automated way, where interface partners are
  simulated in their behavior and message contents are automatically validated, so the correct processing is always ensured.</para>
  
  <para>This document provides a reference guide to all features of the Citrus test framework and it gives a detailed picture 
  of how to set up an automated integration testing environment. Since this document is considered to be under construction, 
  please do not hesitate to give any comments or requests to us using our user or support mailing lists.</para>
  
</preface>