<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="testcase">
  <title>Test case</title>

  <para>Now let us start writing test cases! The following guide will introduce all possible actions inside a test case 
  and explain how to connect to other systems by sending and receiving messages over various transports.</para>
  
  <para>Citrus specifies test cases through simple XML files. The whole test case description will take place in one single
  XML file. This chapter will introduce the custom XML schema language that defines a test cases.</para>

  <section id="testcase-defining">
    <title>Defining a test case</title>

    <para>Clearly spoken a test case is nothing but a simple Spring XML configuration file. 
    So using the Spring XML configuration syntax you are able to write fully compatible test cases for the Citrus framework.</para>
    
    <programlisting>
  &lt;beans
      xmlns=&quot;http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans&quot;
      xmlns:xsi=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance&quot;
      xsi:schemaLocation=&quot;http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans
      http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans-2.5.xsd&quot;&gt;
      
      &lt;bean name=&quot;myFirstTest&quot; 
               class=&quot;com.consol.citrus.model.TestCase&quot;&gt;
          &lt;property name=&quot;actions&quot;&gt;
              <lineannotation>&lt;!-- actions of this test go here --&gt;</lineannotation>
          &lt;/property&gt;
      &lt;/bean&gt;
  &lt;/beans&gt;
    </programlisting>
    
    <para>Citrus can execute these test case as normal test cases - no problem, but this XML usual 
    syntax is not the best way to describe a test case in Citrus, especially when test scenarios get more 
    complex and the test cases grow in size. Therefore Citrus provides a custom XML schema definition for 
    writing test cases.</para>
    
    <para>The custom XML schema aims to reach the convenience of Domain specific languages (DSL). Let us have a look 
    at the Citrus test describing DSL by introducing a first very simple test case definition:</para>
    
    <programlisting>
  &lt;spring:beans
      xmlns=&quot;http://www.citrusframework.org/schema/testcase&quot;
      xmlns:xsi=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance&quot;
      xmlns:spring=&quot;http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans&quot;
      xsi:schemaLocation=&quot;
      http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans 
      http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans-2.5.xsd
      http://www.citrusframework.org/schema/testcase 
      http://www.citrusframework.org/schema/testcase/citrus-testcase.xsd&quot;&gt;
      
      &lt;testcase name=&quot;myFirstTest&quot;&gt;
          &lt;description&gt;
              First example showing the basic test case definition elements!
          &lt;/description&gt;
          &lt;variables&gt;
              &lt;variable name=&quot;text&quot; 
                           value=&quot;Hello Test Framework&quot;/&gt;
          &lt;/variables&gt;
          &lt;actions&gt;
              &lt;echo&gt;
                  &lt;message&gt;${test}&lt;/message&gt;
              &lt;/echo&gt;
          &lt;/actions&gt;
      &lt;/testcase&gt;
  &lt;/spring:beans&gt;
    </programlisting>
    
    <para>We do need the <literal>&lt;spring:beans&gt;</literal> root element as the XML file is read by the Spring IoC Container. 
    Inside this root element the Citrus specific namespace definitions take place. In the following we use the customized XML schema 
    language in Citrus to describe the test case.</para>
    
    <para>The test case itself gets a mandatory name that must be unique throughout all test cases in a project. You will receive errors
    when using duplicate test names. The name must not contain any whitespaces but does support special characters like '-', '.', '_'. 
    The &lt;testcase&gt; element holds several child elements. These basic test elements are described in the following sections.</para>
    
    <section id="testcase-description">
        <title>Description</title>
        
        <para>The test case description points out the purpose and gives a short introduction to the intended use case scenario that 
        will be tested. The user should get a first impression what the test case is all about. You can use free text in order to describe the test. 
        But be aware of the XML validation rules of well formed XML (e.g. special character escaping, use of CDATA sections)</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="testcase-variables">
        <title>Variables</title>
        
        <programlisting>
  &lt;variables&gt;
      &lt;variable name=&quot;text&quot; value=&quot;Hello Test Framework&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;variable name=&quot;customerId&quot; value=&quot;123456789&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;/variables&gt;
        </programlisting>
        
        <para>The test variables are valid for the whole test case. You can reference them several times using a variables expression 
        <literal>"${variable-name}"</literal>. It is good practice to provide all important entities as test variables. This
        makes the test easier to maintain and more flexible. All essential entities are present right at the beginning of the test, which
        may also give the opportunity to easily create test variants by simply changing the variable values.</para>
        
        <para>The name of the variable is arbitrary. Feel free to specify any name you can think of. Of course you need to be careful with
        special characters and reserved XML entities like '&amp;', '&lt;', '&gt;'. If you are familiar with Java or any other programming 
        language simply think of the naming rules there and you will be fine with working on Citrus variables too. The value of a variable 
        can be any character sequence. But again be aware of special XML characters like "&lt;" that need to be escaped ("&amp;lt;") when 
        used in variable values.</para>
        
        <para>The advantage of variables is obvious. Once declared the variables can be referenced many times in
        the test. This makes it very easy to vary different test cases by adjusting the variables for different means (e.g. use different 
        error codes in test cases).</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="testcase-actions">
        <title>Actions</title>
        
        <para>A test case defines a sequence of actions that will take place during the test. The
        actions are executed sequentially as they are defined in the test case definition.</para>
        
        <programlisting>
  &lt;actions&gt;
      &lt;action&gt;[...]&lt;/action&gt;
      &lt;action&gt;[...]&lt;/action&gt;
      &lt;action&gt;[...]&lt;/action&gt;
      &lt;action&gt;[...]&lt;/action&gt;
  &lt;/actions&gt;
        </programlisting>
        
        <para>All actions have individual names and properties that define 
        the action behavior. Citrus offers a wide range of test actions from scratch, but you are also able to write your own 
        test actions in Java or Groovy and execute them during a test. <xref linkend="actions"/> gives you a brief description of all available 
        actions that can be part of a test case execution.</para>
        
        <para>The actions are combined in free sequence to each other so that the tester is able to declare a special action chain inside the test.
        These actions can be sending or receiving messages, delaying the test, validating the database and so on. Step by step the test proceeds 
        the action chain. Usually the tester tries to fit the designed use case scenario with the action chain.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="testcase-finally">
        <title>Cleanup</title>
        
        <para>The finally element also contains a list of test actions. These actions will be executed at the very
        end of the test case even if errors did occur during the execution before. This is the right place to tidy up things that were previously 
        created by the test like cleaning up the database for instance. The finally section is described in more detail in <xref linkend="finally"/></para>
  
        <programlisting>      
  &lt;finally&gt;
      &lt;action&gt;[...]&lt;/action&gt;
      &lt;action&gt;[...]&lt;/action&gt;
      &lt;action&gt;[...]&lt;/action&gt;
      &lt;action&gt;[...]&lt;/action&gt;
  &lt;/finally&gt;
        </programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="testcase-metainfo">
    <title>Meta information</title>

    <para>The user can provide some basic information about the test case. The meta-info element at the very beginning of the test case 
    holds information like the author of the test or the creation date. In detail the meta information is specified like this:</para>
    
    <programlisting>
  &lt;testcase name=&quot;metaInfoTest&quot;&gt;
      &lt;meta-info&gt;
          &lt;author&gt;Christoph Deppisch&lt;/author&gt;
          &lt;creationdate&gt;2008-01-11&lt;/creationdate&gt;
          &lt;status&gt;FINAL&lt;/status&gt;
          &lt;last-updated-by&gt;Christoph Deppisch&lt;/last-updated-by&gt;
          &lt;last-updated-on&gt;2008-01-11T10:00:00&lt;/last-updated-on&gt;
      &lt;/meta-info&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;
          ...
      &lt;/description&gt;
      &lt;actions&gt;
          ...
      &lt;/actions&gt;
  &lt;/testcase&gt;
    </programlisting>
    
    <para>The status allows following values: DRAFT, READY_FOR_REVIEW, DISABLED, FINAL.
    The meta-data information to a test is quite important to give the reader a first information about
    the test. It is also possible to generate test documentation using this meta-data information. The built-in Citrus 
    documentation generates HTML or Excel documents that list all tests with their metadata information and description.</para>
    
    <note>
        <para>Tests in status DISABLED will not be executed during a test suite run. So someone can just start adding
        planned test cases that are not finished yet in status DRAFT. In case a test is not runnable yet because not finished entirely
        someone may disable a test temporarily to avoid causing failures during a test run. Using these different status one can 
        easily set up test plans and review the progress of test coverage by comparing the amount of test in status DRAFT to those in FINAL state.</para>
    </note>
    
  </section>
  
</chapter>