<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0"
          xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/changes-1.0.0.xsd">
  <properties>
    <title>Jolokia</title>
    <author email="roland@jolokia.org">Roland Huß</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <release version="0.91" description="Release 0.91" date="">
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2011-5-26">
        Fixed issue with overloaded methods where one variant takes no
        arguments. This no-arg variant can be specified with the
        signature "()" after the operation name.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-04-23">
        Added HTTPS support for the JVM-JDK6 agent. In order to switch
        it on, the property "protocol=https" must be set and
        additional the properties "keystore" and "keystorePassword"
        for pointing to the keystore which holds the server side
        certificate. Client side certificate authentication is
        switched off currently alway.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2011-04-18">
        Fixed date handling when an MBean exports an attribute as
        date. It is now returned as an ISO-8601 formatted string, when
        used with a path "time" the epoch milliseconds are
        returned. Setting of date values and using dates as arguments
        for JMX operations is now also supported, the value can be
        given either in epoch milliseconds or as an ISO-86-1 formatted
        string. With a path "time" a given date value can be even
        updated for a write operation.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-04-14">
        Reworked "list" handling. It's no much faster when used with
        pathes since it doesn't slurp in the whole meta and truncate
        it afterwards but does the right thing directly to only fetch
        the required information. The list handler respect now a
        'maxDepth' request option for truncating the data from top
        down. 'maxDepth' works with pathes, too. Comprehensive unit
        tests has been added as well.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-04-04">
        Added constructor to J4pListRequest() which takes an
        ObjectName as argument for fetching the meta data for a single
        MBean only.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.90" description="Release 0.90" date="2011-04-04">
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-04-04">
        Added a Knopflerfish detector and tested Jolokia with Knopflerfish 3.1
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2011-03-28">
        Fixed content-type in javascript library to "text/json" for requests
        (was "application/x-www-form-urlencoded")
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-03-26">
        A search request will now return an empty list, not an error
        response with a 404 status code. A null result of a search
        query is considered to be a valid result, not an error
        condition.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-03-24">
        Added a OSGi bundle property org.jolokia.listenForHttpService
        which, if set to false, prevents the automatic registration of
        a JolokiaServlet to an OSGi HttpService (default: true)
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-03-24">
        The activator in jolokia-osgi and jolokia-osgi-bundle can now
        use an OSGi restrictor service implementing
        org.jolokia.restrictor.Restrictor when bundle property 
        org.jolokia.useRestrictorService is set to true.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-03-24">
        Added a servlet init parameter "policyLocation" for specifying
        the location of the policy file. This can be an URL or an
        string with prefix "classpath:". Default:
        "classpath:/jolokia-access.xml" 
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-03-24">
        Refactored restrictor handling and exported
        org.jolokia.restrictor in the OSGi bundles. JolokiaServlet can 
        take now an Restrictor object as constructor parameter.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-03-24">
        Lookup of policy file with the same classloader as used for
        loading the jolokia classes if lookup failed with context
        loader added.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-03-16">
        jolokia.js: Works now with jQuery 1.5.1, too (but still doesn't use 
        the advanced Ajax features)
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-03-16">
        jolokia.js: Added an HTTP method upgrade to "post" if a proxy
        target is provided.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-03-16">
        jolokia.js: Add a trailing slash to the Jolokia URL if a
        "post" request is requested.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-03-04">
        Changed protocol in order to support JSON types for return
        values and write/exec parameters instead of only plain strings
        as it was before.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.83" description="Release 0.83" date="2001-02-19">
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-02-15">
        Reference Manual updated with sections about the OSGi agent
        and the new Roo addon.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-02-17">
        Jolokia Roo addon added.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-02-15">
        Added a Virgo detector (tested with 2.1)
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-02-11">
        Added PGP signing for the deployed artifacts
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-02-11">
        Introduced org.jolokia.osgi.servlet.JolokiaServlet which gets exported by the jolokia-osgi
        bundle and allows for programmatic registration of the servlet without the use of an
        OSGi HttpService.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-02-05">
        Update jolokia-osgi-bundle to include Felix's HttpService implementation
        (since its is a bit smaller and fits better due to the packages already
        included). Now the bundle can be deployed without dependencies at all on Felix
        and Equinox. I recommend to use the 'pure' bundle and a given HttpService, though.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2011-01-25">
        Fixed problem for Jetty Detector with Jetty Version &lt; 6.1.4 and made
        server detection to more conservative so that the servlet starts up nevertheless
        when an exception occurs during the detection phase (call in the servlet's init method).
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2011-02-01">
        Fixed registering of simplifiers, which allows for simplified serialization of
        well known objects like java.io.File or javax.management.ObjectName
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.82" description="Release 0.82" date="2011-01-16">
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-01-08">
        The HTTP status code returned with a HTTP response does not reflect the
        status of the JMX operation itself. An HTTP error occurs only if an processing
        exception (like security constraint violations) happen on the top agent level,
        otherwise 200 is returned (even when an Jolokia response object contains an error).
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-01-16">
        Added a Javascript client library including about 120 unit
        tests and a new section in the reference manual.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.81" description="Release 0.81" date="2010-12-14">
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2010-10-24">
        Fixed MBean registration issue with Websphere AS 7.0 where
        MBean registration via the MBeanRegistration intefaces causes
        the WAS MBeanServer to raise a NPE (but register the MBean
        nevertheless, so no rollback here). 
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2010-10-24">
        New request parameter "callback" allows for sending a response
        as JavaScript function (JSONP). For POST request this
        parameter must be given as URL parameter and is valid for bulk
        requests, too.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2010-10-24">
        Security policy can now be globally restricted to a certain
        HTTP method.  Within the &lt;http&gt; section of the policy
        file, &lt;method&gt; tags define the allowed methods ("get" or
        "post"). If this section is missing, all methods are
        allowed. If only one method is given, the other is forbidden.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2010-11-04">
        Added an alias for MBean "jmx4perl:type=Config"
        to "jolokia:type=Config" for backwards compatibility with jmx4perl
        clients &lt; 0.80
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2010-11-27" issue="GIT-14">
        Change HttpClient to a thread safe connection manager by default,
        extended J4pClient construction with a builder pattern
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2010-12-10">
        Added a server detection facility (available via the 'version' command)
        and made 'version' the default command if no command is given in the request URL
        for a GET request.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2010-12-10">
        Added a "error_type" key to the Jolokia response in case of an remote exception,
        which will contain the Java class name of this error. Added getErrorType() to
        the J4pRemoteException for the Java-Client.
      </action>
    </release>
  </body>
</document>