<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
  ~ Copyright 2009-2013 Roland Huss
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0"
          xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/changes-1.0.0.xsd">
  <properties>
    <title>Jolokia</title>
    <author email="roland@jolokia.org">Roland Huß</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <release version="1.1.1-SNAPSHOT" description="Release 1.1.1-SNAPSHOT">
      <action dev="benson-basis" type="add" issue="86" date="2013-03-13">
        If no host is given, the JVM agent will now bind to localhost. If a
        host of "0.0.0.0" or "*" is given, then the agent will listen on
        all interfaces.
      </action>
      <action dev="benson-basis" type="add" issue="82" date="2013-03-13">
        If a port of 0 is given, then the JVM agent will select an arbitrary
        free port and prints out the selected port.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" issue="77" date="2013-03-07">
        Added support for "ifModifiedSince" processing parameter.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" issue="83" date="2013-03-06">
        Fixed wrong key order in path when diving into tabular data values.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" issue="76" date="2013-03-01">
        Check whether the Jolokia MBeanServerHolder is registered in advance instead of relying on
        an InstanceNotFoundException
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" issue="79" date="2013-03-01">
        Added BigDecimal and BigInteger converters for input parameters
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="1.1.0" description="Release 1.1.0" date="2013-02-28">
      <action dev="mjr5749" type="fix" date="2013-02-22" issue="67">
        Fix a bug HistoryEntry.trim() when the list of values is empty and max duration is > 0
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2013-02-21">
        Added enums for serialization/deserialization. It's really surprising how long
        this missing feature slipped without anybody missing it ;-)
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2013-02-20" issue="66">
        Added additional query parameters (serializeException, canonicalNaming and includeStackTrace)
        to the set of allowed query parameters for the Java client lib.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2013-02-12" issue="64">
        Fixed URI encoding for GET requests in the JavaScript client library.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2013-02-11">
        Added safety net for serialization, so that OutputStreams and Writers are never
        obtained from get-methods if they declare a subclass as return value. It happens e.g. for
        Jetty 8.1 that FileResource.getOutputStream() opens a new FileOutputStream nuking the
        existing data. Nice side effect ;-)
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2013-02-07" issue="59">
        Added new global and process configuration options "includeStackTrace" (true,false,runtime)
        and "serializeException" (true, false) which can be used to tune the
        error responses.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2013-02-07" issue="59">
        "canonicalNaming" option can be as global agent configuration, too.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2013-02-07" issue="63">
        Fixed Glassfish detector which failed to boot AMX in certain circumstances.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2013-01-27">
        Added support for JSON-MBean. A dedicated @JsonMBean annotation can be used
        to export complex arguments/attributes/return values as JSON String to the Platform
        MBeanServer. Jolokia now offers an own MBeanServer as well for registering MBeans which
        won't show up in any other (exported) MBeanServer (except for the delegation of @JsonMBeans
        which are delegated and translated).
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2013-01-13">
        Fixed issues with GET requests and MBean ObjectNames which end with a "/".
        Added to integration tests to deal with these issues.
      </action>
      <action dev="twhite" type="fix" date="2013-01-04">
        Fixed timestamp in the Java client library's response.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2012-12-30">
        New module "jolokia-spring" with Spring integration for the
        JVM agent has been added. It contains an own Spring
        configuration syntax and provides also a plugin for automatic
        startup the agent with default values by only declaring a
        dependency (works for containers which automatically lookup
        META-INF/spring/*.xml). Kudos to James Strachan for the
        initial idea.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.6" description="Release 1.0.6" date="2012-11-26">
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2012-08-14">
        Jolokia's Javascript poller fixes an register/unregister issue, where the returned
        handle from register() remains stable.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2012-07-27">
        Jolokia JVM agent used with startup options now initializes
        itself lazily in order to await all the MBeans required for a
        proper server detection.
      </action>
      <action dev="mikael,jstrachan,roland" type="add" date="2012-10-10">
        One can now change the key property order for MBeans names with the query parameter "canonicalNaming" 
        for read, list and search operations. By default this is set to "true" in which case
        an alphabetical ordering for the keys is used. If set to "false", then the original name as registered
        is used. 
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2012-11-23">
        Added a method "jobs()" to the JavaScript Jolokia agent to get all handles for all currently registered
        jobs.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2012-11-25">
        Added GlassfishDetector to the list of detectors for the OSGi Agent.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.5" description="Release 1.0.5" date="2012-07-23">
      <action dev="matejj" type="add" date="2012-07-19" issue="JOL-35">
        Added a deserialization to javax.management.ObjectName so that attributes of
        this type and operations taking such an argument can be properly invoked
        with a Jolokia request.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2012-06-25">
        Added Jolokia datasource for Cubism (with AMD support).
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2012-06-25">
        Jolokia WAR agent initialisation parameters can now be given as servlet context
        parameters, too.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2012-06-12">
        Fixed regular expression for detecting Oracle Glassfish server
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2012-06-12">
        Added specific check for 7.1.x to JBoss Handler since for 7.1 there seems
        to be an MBean for the version number (contrary to 7.0.x)
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.4" description="Release 1.0.4" date="2012-06-07">
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2012-06-06">
        Allow for custom detector options in the agent's
        configuration. These options can be evaluated during startup
        of the agent. The first (and only) option it 'bootAmx' for
        allowing a Glassfish detector to not boot up the AMX subsystem
        upon start of this agent. By default (since it is probably
        needed every time when Jolokia is installed), AMX is booted to
        provide the most userful information over JMX.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2012-06-05">
        Added a page showing the Jolokia-Cubism integration including
        live demos. 
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2012-05-16">
        Added a scheduler to the JavaScript client library.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2012-04-20">
        Fixed issue with HTTP method checker for policy based restrictions.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2012-04-26">
        Fixed fallback when registering ConfigMBean which didn't
        properly work (see pull request #42)  
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.3" description="Release 1.0.3" date="2012-04-11">
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2012-02-09">
        Fixed issue with Glassfish detector and Jolokia running under gcj
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2012-01-30">
        Added support for AMD in jolokia.js and jolokia-simple.js
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2012-03-06">
        The history store allows also for time based eviction (JOL-28)
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2012-03-24">
        Fix for possible NPE when serializing a complex Java objects (#41)
      </action>
      <action dev="gid79" type="add" date="2012-03-25">
        New configuration property "httpServiceFilter" added for providing
        a OSGi filter expression which gets applied when selecting the HttpService
        to bind to. (#39)
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2012-03-26">
        If registering of an ConfigMBean doesnt work because there has been already one be
        registered with the same name by another agent, a warning is giving out and a UUID is adde to
        the object name, so startup works as usual. Use either a "mbeanQualifier" or an "httpServiceFilter" in
        order to avoid naming collisions from the very beginning.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2012-04-09" issue="JOL-27">
        Added CORS support for the agents including preflight checks. The policy
        based restrictor allows for fine grained restriction of cross
        origin access with a &lt;cors&gt; section.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2012-04-10">
        Added none-caching headers (cache-control: 'no-cache', pragma: 'no-cache', expires: '-1') to
        Jolokia's response for all requests.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.2" description="Release 1.0.2" date="2012-01-06">
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-12-29">
        Verified that javascript client binding works with jQuery 1.7.1
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-12-29">
        Updated Roo plugin for Roo 1.2. It won't work with older Roo
        versions.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-12-27">
        Jolokia's Java client library now can request MBeans via an
        JSR-160 proxy. This is done either by giving a default proxy
        configuration to the J4pClient or by providing a proxy config
        to the request objects.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-12-15">
        Added support for global and request procession parameter
        "mimeType" for specifying the HTTP content-type for the
        Jolokia response. By default this is "text/plain" (but
        "application/json" can be useful, too).
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-12-16">
        In case of an error, the request leading to this error is
        returned in the response, too.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.1" description="Release 1.0.1" date="2011-10-31">
      <action dev="senthilnest" type="fix" date="2011-10-29" issue="37">
        Daemonized threads created by the thread pool for the JVM agent.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-10-18">
        Added a CollectionConverter for deserializing collections in
        addition to Maps and Lists.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-10-12">
        The JVM agent know can also take as argument a regular
        expression for matching a process' name in adition to a
        process id.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2011-10-8">
        Fixed path access which consists of a single slash (which is
        the same as no path at all).
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.0" description="Release 1.0.0" date="2011-10-03">
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-9-12">
        Applied patch from codewax for supporting an Equinox HTTP-Service
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2011-9-12">
        Increased test coverage to 80.5%, documented public API to
        100% (plus 100% rules coverage, 0% duplications, 0% package
        tangle index ...). See
        http://labs.consol.de/sonar/dashboard/index/org.jolokia:jolokia
        for more informations about Jolokia's code metrics.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2011-9-14">
        Fixed problem with URL encoding for GET request with the Java
        client library, which used to use URLEncoder.encode() and
        switched now to URI. See
        http://stackoverflow.com/questions/724043/http-url-address-encoding-in-java
        for details.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-9-15">
        Added processing options for the Java client
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-9-22">
        Changed escaping scheme for GET URLs and paths so that a
        slash (/) can be escaped with an exclamation mark (!): / -->
        !/
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-9-27">
        Multiple attibutes can be added to GET read requests as a
        comma separated value list within the URL.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.95" description="Release 0.95" date="2011-08-21">
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-7-29">
        Added a dynamical attach mode for the JVM agent launcher (patch
        by Greg Bowyer).  The agent now includes also a client for
        dynamically starting/stoping an agent on already running Java
        process. See the reference manual for more information.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-8-7">
        Support for upstream serialization of open type,
        i.e. CompositeData and TabularData.  This allows for easy
        access to MXBeans, which provide support of transparent
        translation between plain Java objects and collections, which
        follow some restrictions, to open type data. Jolokia knows how
        to deal with the fixed format used by this MXBean translation
        of Maps and transparentrly dispatch this to a JSON
        map. Initial patch provided by asssaf.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.91" description="Release 0.91" date="2011-05-30">
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2011-5-26">
        Fixed issue with overloaded methods where one variant takes no
        arguments. This no-arg variant can be specified with the
        signature "()" after the operation name.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-04-23">
        Added HTTPS support for the JVM agent. In order to switch
        it on, the property "protocol=https" must be set and
        additional the properties "keystore" and "keystorePassword"
        for pointing to the keystore which holds the server side
        certificate. Client side certificate authentication is
        switched off currently alway.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2011-04-18">
        Fixed date handling when an MBean exports an attribute as
        date. It is now returned as an ISO-8601 formatted string, when
        used with a path "time" the epoch milliseconds are
        returned. Setting of date values and using dates as arguments
        for JMX operations is now also supported, the value can be
        given either in epoch milliseconds or as an ISO-86-1 formatted
        string. With a path "time" a given date value can be even
        updated for a write operation.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-04-14">
        Reworked "list" handling. It's now much faster when used with
        paths since it doesn't slurp in the whole meta and truncate
        it afterwards but does the right thing directly to only fetch
        the required information. The list handler respect now a
        'maxDepth' request option for truncating the data from top
        down. 'maxDepth' works with paths, too. Comprehensive unit
        tests has been added as well.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-04-04">
        Added constructor to J4pListRequest() which takes an
        ObjectName as argument for fetching the meta data for a single
        MBean only.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.90" description="Release 0.90" date="2011-04-04">
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-04-04">
        Added a Knopflerfish detector and tested Jolokia with Knopflerfish 3.1
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2011-03-28">
        Fixed content-type in javascript library to "text/json" for requests
        (was "application/x-www-form-urlencoded")
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-03-26">
        A search request will now return an empty list, not an error
        response with a 404 status code. A null result of a search
        query is considered to be a valid result, not an error
        condition.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-03-24">
        Added a OSGi bundle property org.jolokia.listenForHttpService
        which, if set to false, prevents the automatic registration of
        a JolokiaServlet to an OSGi HttpService (default: true)
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-03-24">
        The activator in jolokia-osgi and jolokia-osgi-bundle can now
        use an OSGi restrictor service implementing
        org.jolokia.restrictor.Restrictor when bundle property 
        org.jolokia.useRestrictorService is set to true.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-03-24">
        Added a servlet init parameter "policyLocation" for specifying
        the location of the policy file. This can be an URL or an
        string with prefix "classpath:". Default:
        "classpath:/jolokia-access.xml" 
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-03-24">
        Refactored restrictor handling and exported
        org.jolokia.restrictor in the OSGi bundles. JolokiaServlet can 
        take now an Restrictor object as constructor parameter.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-03-24">
        Lookup of policy file with the same classloader as used for
        loading the jolokia classes if lookup failed with context
        loader added.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-03-16">
        jolokia.js: Works now with jQuery 1.5.1, too (but still doesn't use 
        the advanced Ajax features)
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-03-16">
        jolokia.js: Added an HTTP method upgrade to "post" if a proxy
        target is provided.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-03-16">
        jolokia.js: Add a trailing slash to the Jolokia URL if a
        "post" request is requested.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-03-04">
        Changed protocol in order to support JSON types for return
        values and write/exec parameters instead of only plain strings
        as it was before.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.83" description="Release 0.83" date="2011-02-19">
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-02-15">
        Reference Manual updated with sections about the OSGi agent
        and the new Roo addon.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-02-17">
        Jolokia Roo addon added.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-02-15">
        Added a Virgo detector (tested with 2.1)
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-02-11">
        Added PGP signing for the deployed artifacts
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-02-11">
        Introduced org.jolokia.osgi.servlet.JolokiaServlet which gets exported by the jolokia-osgi
        bundle and allows for programmatic registration of the servlet without the use of an
        OSGi HttpService.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-02-05">
        Update jolokia-osgi-bundle to include Felix's HttpService implementation
        (since its is a bit smaller and fits better due to the packages already
        included). Now the bundle can be deployed without dependencies at all on Felix
        and Equinox. I recommend to use the 'pure' bundle and a given HttpService, though.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2011-01-25">
        Fixed problem for Jetty Detector with Jetty Version &lt; 6.1.4 and made
        server detection to more conservative so that the servlet starts up nevertheless
        when an exception occurs during the detection phase (call in the servlet's init method).
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2011-02-01">
        Fixed registering of simplifiers, which allows for simplified serialization of
        well known objects like java.io.File or javax.management.ObjectName
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.82" description="Release 0.82" date="2011-01-16">
      <action dev="roland" type="update" date="2011-01-08">
        The HTTP status code returned with a HTTP response does not reflect the
        status of the JMX operation itself. An HTTP error occurs only if an processing
        exception (like security constraint violations) happen on the top agent level,
        otherwise 200 is returned (even when an Jolokia response object contains an error).
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2011-01-16">
        Added a Javascript client library including about 120 unit
        tests and a new section in the reference manual.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.81" description="Release 0.81" date="2010-12-14">
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2010-10-24">
        Fixed MBean registration issue with Websphere AS 7.0 where
        MBean registration via the MBeanRegistration intefaces causes
        the WAS MBeanServer to raise a NPE (but register the MBean
        nevertheless, so no rollback here). 
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2010-10-24">
        New request parameter "callback" allows for sending a response
        as JavaScript function (JSONP). For POST request this
        parameter must be given as URL parameter and is valid for bulk
        requests, too.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2010-10-24">
        Security policy can now be globally restricted to a certain
        HTTP method.  Within the &lt;http&gt; section of the policy
        file, &lt;method&gt; tags define the allowed methods ("get" or
        "post"). If this section is missing, all methods are
        allowed. If only one method is given, the other is forbidden.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2010-11-04">
        Added an alias for MBean "jmx4perl:type=Config"
        to "jolokia:type=Config" for backwards compatibility with jmx4perl
        clients &lt; 0.80
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="fix" date="2010-11-27" issue="14">
        Change HttpClient to a thread safe connection manager by default,
        extended J4pClient construction with a builder pattern
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2010-12-10">
        Added a server detection facility (available via the 'version' command)
        and made 'version' the default command if no command is given in the request URL
        for a GET request.
      </action>
      <action dev="roland" type="add" date="2010-12-10">
        Added a "error_type" key to the Jolokia response in case of an remote exception,
        which will contain the Java class name of this error. Added getErrorType() to
        the J4pRemoteException for the Java-Client.
      </action>
    </release>
  </body>
</document>
