<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  
  <properties>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <author email="roland@jolokia.org">Roland Huss</author>
  </properties>

  <head>
    <meta name="description" content="Jolokia is an alternative to JSR-160 connectors for remote JMX access. It provides REST-like access to JMX with JSON over HTTP."/>
    <link rel="alternate" 
          type="application/rss+xml" 
          title="Jolokia" 
          href="http://labs.consol.de/tags/jolokia/feed" />
  </head>

  <body>
    <div class="teaser">
      <strong>Jolokia</strong> is remote JMX with JSON over HTTP.<br/>
      <div class="subtitle">It is fast, simple, polyglot and has unique features. 
      It's JMX on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capsaicin">Capsaicin</a>.</div>
    </div>
    <p>
      Jolokia is a JMX-HTTP bridge giving an alternative to JSR-160
      connectors.  It is an agent based approach with support for many
      platforms. In addition to basic JMX operations it enhances JMX
      remoting with unique features like bulk requests or fine grained
      security policies. 
    </p>
    <subsection name="Starting points">
      <ul>
        <li>
          Overview of <a href="features-nb.html">Features</a> which
          make Jolokia unique for JMX remoting.
        </li>
        <li>          
          The <a href="documentation.html">Documentation</a> includes
          a <a href="tutorial.html">tutorial</a> and a <a
          href="reference/html/index.html">reference manual</a>.
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="agent.html">Agents</a> are available for many
          platforms (JEE, OSGi, Mule, JDK6 JVM).          
        </li>
        <li>
          The <a href="support.html">support</a> page contains
          information for how to get Jolokia support and how to
          participate in the evolution of Jolokia.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </subsection>
    <section name="News">
      <subsection name="Jolokia 0.90 has landed">
        <div class="news-date">2011-04-04</div>
        <p>
          This release starts the final round before 1.0 (expected
          late this summer). It concentrates on polishing and
          improvement of existing features and minor changes to the
          JSON protocol.
        </p>
        <p>
          The OSGi agent has been revisited again for better
          subclassing hooks and the possibility to lookup a Restrictor
          service. Knopflerfish 3.1 has been added to the list of
          tested platforms.
        </p>
        <p>
          The JSON protocol has been changed to support native numbers
          and booleans instead of using them as strings only. The
          upstream serialization to the agent has been extended to
          better support arrays and maps with JSON data types
          (strings, numbers, booleans).
        </p>
        <p>
          Policy file can now be looked up in several places, which
          must be loadable with an URL. Own restrictors can be plugged
          in easily in the agent's servlet. 
        </p>
        <p>
          The reference manual has some more section on the <a
          href="reference/html/architecture.html">architecture</a>, a
          chapter about Jolokia <a
          href="reference/html/security.html">security</a> and the <a
          href="reference/html/agents.html#agents-war">war
          agent</a>. It still needs some proof reading, though.
        </p>
        <p>
          As always, these and more changes are listed in the <a
          href="changes-report.html">change log</a>. Please expect for
          the 0.9x series some minor (hopefully backwards compatible)
          changes in the protocol and internal package structure (also
          to keep <a
          href="http://labs.consol.de/sonar/dashboard/index/946">Sonar</a>
          happy ;-).
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Jolokia 0.83 released">
        <div class="news-date">2011-02-19</div>
        <p>
          A brand new <a
          href="http://www.springsource.org/roo">Roo</a> addon for
          integrating Jolokia into a Roo managed web project. It will
          register a Jolokia agent servlet into the project's
          web.xml. More about this add-on can be found in the <a
          href="reference/html/tools.html#tools-roo">reference
          manual</a>.
        </p>
        <p>
          The OSGi agents have been revisited and the all-in-one
          bundle has been fine tuned. The reference documentation
          contains now also a section about these <a
          href="reference/html/agents.html#agents-osgi">OSGi
          agents</a>. Furthermore, <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/virgo/">Eclipse Virgo</a> 2.1
          has been added to our test suite and a dedicated Virgo
          server detector has been added. 
        </p>
        <p>
          These and more changes are listed in the <a
          href="changes-report.html">change log</a>.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Jolokia 0.82 released">
        <div class="news-date">2011-01-16</div>
        <p>
          The <a href="client/javascript.html">Jolokia Javascript
          Client Library</a> has arrived. This is the most notable
          addition to this release. It's now a piece of cake to query 
          MBeans from within your Browser dynamically via Ajax calls. 
        </p>
        <p>
          This release contains also a substantial change concerning
          the error handling. In former versions, the HTTP return code
          of a Jolokia request reflected the success status of the JMX
          operation itself. This is no longer the case, the HTTP
          status code will always be 200 as long as the agent could
          perform its work, regardless of any error happened during
          performing the JMX operation. The Jolokia status code
          contained in the returned JSON response indicates the state
          of the JMX operation. This change decouples errors on the
          transport and Jolokia layer making a dedicated error
          handling much easier. When the HTTP code is 200, the
          response contains always a JSON object, that's guaranteed
          now. 
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Jolokia 0.81 released">
        <div class="news-date">2010-12-14</div>
        <p>
          This minor release brings back full backwards compatibility
          with <a
          href="http://search.cpan.org/~roland/jmx4perl-0.73/">jmx4perl
          0.73</a> and the Jolokia agents can be used as drop in
          replacemt for the (deprecated) j4p agents. Beside bug fixes,
          this release also contains some minor addional features like
          JSONP support, a new security configuration parameter for
          restrictions on the HTTP method in use, minor tunings of the
          Java client API and a server detection facility for the
          "version" command. All changes are summarized <a
          href="changes-report.html">here</a>.
        </p>
      </subsection>
  </section>
</body>

</document>

