<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  
  <properties>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <author email="roland@jolokia.org">Roland Huss</author>
  </properties>

  <head>
    <meta name="description" content="Jolokia is an alternative to JSR-160 connectors for remote JMX access. It provides REST-like access to JMX with JSON over HTTP."/>
    <link rel="alternate" 
          type="application/rss+xml" 
          title="Jolokia" 
          href="http://labs.consol.de/tags/jolokia/feed" />
  </head>

  <body>
    <div class="teaser">
      <strong>Jolokia</strong> is remote JMX with JSON over HTTP.<br/>
      <div class="subtitle">It is fast, simple, polyglot and has unique features. 
      It's JMX on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capsaicin">Capsaicin</a>.</div>
    </div>
    <p>
      Jolokia is a JMX-HTTP bridge giving an alternative to JSR-160
      connectors.  It is an agent based approach with support for many
      platforms. In addition to basic JMX operations it enhances JMX
      remoting with unique features like bulk requests and fine grained
      security policies. 
    </p>
    <subsection name="Starting points">
      <ul>
        <li>
          Overview of <a href="features-nb.html">features</a> which
          make Jolokia unique for JMX remoting.
        </li>
        <li>          
          The <a href="documentation.html">documentation</a> includes
          a <a href="tutorial.html">tutorial</a> and a <a
          href="reference/html/index.html">reference manual</a>.
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="agent.html">Agents</a> exist for many
          platforms (JEE, OSGi, Mule, JVM).          
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="support.html">Support</a> channels are available in both <a
          href="support.html#Your_Support_for_Jolokia">directions</a>.
          You are also welcome to add to the <a
          href="support.html#Source">evolution</a> of Jolokia.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </subsection>
    <section name="News">
      <subsection name="Cubism support in 1.0.5">
        <div class="news-date">2012-07-22</div>
        <p>
          Jolokia 1.0.5 has been released. Beside minor <a
          href="changes-report.html">improvements and bug fixes</a>,
          one great new feature has been introduced: As mentioned in
          the last news, Jolokia has now support for <a
          href="http://square.github.com/cubism/">Cubism</a>, a fine
          time series charting library based on <a
          href="http://d3js.org/">d3.js</a>. Cubism provides a new
          support for an innovative charting type, the <a
          href="http://vis.berkeley.edu/papers/horizon/">horizon
          charts</a>:
        </p>
        <div>
          <img src="images/jolokia_cubism_demo_2.png"/><br/>
          <img src="images/jolokia_cubism_demo_1.png"/>
        </div>
        <p>
          A very cool live demo where a Jolokia javascript client
          fetches live data from our servers and plot it with Cubism
          can be found on this <a href="client/javascript-cubism.html">demo page</a>.
        </p>
        <p>
          Jolokia also uses also a <a
          href="http://travis-ci.org/#!/rhuss/jolokia">Travis</a>
          build in addition to our own <a
          href="http://labs.consol.de/hudson">CI Server</a>. (Did I
          mentioned already, that we have a quite I high <a
          href="http://labs.consol.de/sonar/dashboard/index/org.jolokia:jolokia">Sonar</a> score
          ?). Travis is a quite nice addition to Github, and brings CI
          testing to a higher level for sure.
        </p>
        <p>
          That's it for now. My next few month of open-source will be
          spent now on <a href="https://github.com/rhuss/aji">Ají</a>,
          Jolokia's new fancy sister. Sorry for pushing thinks like
          notifications down on the back-log, but it's not forgotten.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="1.0.4 introduces a Javascript request scheduler">
        <div class="news-date">2012-06-07</div>
        <p>
          Beside some <a href="changes-report.html">bug fixes</a> two
          new features are included in this new release:
        </p>
        <p>
          Jolokia's Javascript library has now a scheduler for
          periodically querying the agent. Requests can be registered
          at the agent and all registered requests are sent at once in
          a single bulk request periodically. This is especially
          useful when building up dashboard like web pages with
          multiple charts.
        </p>
        <p>
          The folowing example registers two requests which are called
          every second. The <a
          href="reference/html/clients.html#js-poller">reference
          documentation</a> has all the details.
        </p>
        <pre class="prettyprint lang-javascript">var jolokia = new Jolokia("http://localhost:8080/jolokia");

// Register request along with callback printing out 
// the heap memory usage
jolokia.register(function(resp) {
   console.log("Memory: " + resp.value);
},{ 
    type:"read", 
    mbean:"java.lang:type=Memory", 
    attribute:"HeapMemoryUsage", 
    path:"used"
});

// Start the scheduler for calling the request every second
jolokia.start(1000);</pre>
        <p>
          The scheduler is used by the new Jolokia-<a
          href="http://square.github.com/cubism/">Cubism</a>
          integration for plotting real time JMX data. Please have a
          look at the <a href="client/javascript-cubism.html">demo
          page</a> for more information about using Jolokia together
          with Cubism.
        </p>
        <p>
          On the agent side detectors now support custom options. The
          first option available is for the Glassfish detector to
          prevent booting of the AMX subsystem, which registers the
          most interesting MBeans. AMX is booted now by default on the
          first request when running in Glassfish. For more
          information, please refer to the <a
          href="reference/html/agents.html#war-agent-installation">WAR
          configuration options</a> in the reference documentation.
        </p>
        <p>
          <a href="https://github.com/rhuss/aji">Ají</a> moves on,
          too, although slower than expected. The main focus of the
          next months will to be bring that Javascript JMX application
          on and out. Stay tuned ...
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="1.0.3 with CORS support">
        <div class="news-date">2012-04-11</div>
        <p>
          This minor release adds cross-origin resource sharing (<a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/cors/">CORS</a>)
          support to all Jolokia agents. Cross domain access can be
          easily restricted with Jolokia's <a
                href="features/security.html">security setup</a>. The <a
                href="client/javascript.html">Javascript</a> library already
          support CORS for most browsers out of the box, for IE8 and
          larger some special setup is still required. Transparent
          CORS client support for all browsers will be added to the
          Jolokia Javascript client in one of the next releases.
        </p>
        <p>
          In addition the following new features were added:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li><a
                  href="https://github.com/amdjs/amdjs-api/wiki/AMD">AMD</a>
            support for jolokia.js and jolokia-simple.js</li>
          <li>Time based eviction of historical values remembered on
            the client side, in addition to count based eviction</li>
          <li>New configuration option <code>httpServiceFilter</code>
            for the OSGi agent for selection of a specific HttpService
            to bind to.</li>
          <li>None-caching headers added to the response</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          All thdeses changes plus the bug fixes are listed in the <a
                href="changes-report.html">change log</a>.
        </p>
        <p>
          Starting with this release, bug tracking and release planning
          switches over to Jolokia's <a
                href="http://jolokia.jira.com">JIRA</a> instance, kindly
          donated by the fine folks from <a
                href="http://www.atlassian.com">Atlassian</a>.
        </p>
        <p>
          Also, there has been some (minor) progress with the new kid in
          the Chili garden, <a
                href="https://github.com/rhuss/aji">Ají</a>, a Javascript
          single-page-application with an MBeanBrowser and a
          Dashboard. I'm still looking for helping hands, there is
          quite a lot to do here ;-)
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="1.0.2 released">
        <div class="news-date">2012-01-06</div>
        <p>
          The first release of this year brings some updates and minor features:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>The Java client library supports now using a JSR-160
          proxy, too. The <a
          href="reference/html/clients.html#client-java">reference
          manual</a> tells you how to 
          provide a proxy either as a default to a
          <code>J4pClient</code> or per request.</li>

          <li>A configuration parameter <code>mimeType</code> can be
          either used in the global configuration or as request
          parameter in order to explicitely set the mime type of the
          returned JSON answer. By default this is <code>text/plain</code>,
          but for some environments a mime type
          <code>application/json</code> might be more
          appropriate.</li>

          <li>In case of an error on the server side, the Jolokia request
          leading to this error is included into the response the same
          way as it is done for successful responses.</li>
          
          <li>The Roo plugin has been updated for Roo 1.2 and the
          Jolokia Javascript library has been tested with the latest
          jQuery version 1.7.1</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          The complete changes are listed in the <a
          href="changes-report.html">change log</a>. BTW, Jolokia is
          available now on <a href="http://search.maven.org">Maven
          central</a>, too. 
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Happy new year 2012 !">
        <div class="news-date">2011-12-29</div>
        <p>
          This was an exciting year for Jolokia:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>We hit 1.0.0 in October after one year of active development</li>
          <li>Jolokia was presented at <a
          href="http://www.devoxx.com">Devoxx 2011</a> in the
          "<em>Tools in action</em>" track. Despite the competition on
          the parallel tracks was very strong and some technical issues, I
          think the talk went rather well (although there is of course
          quite some space for improvement ;-). I blogged about my
          <a
          href="http://labs.consol.de/blog/devoxx/devoxx-2011-day-1/#jolokia">experience</a>
          and you can find the <a
          href="http://www.parleys.com/d/2864">full talk</a> recorded
          at Parleys. In order to see the full talk you either need to
          wait a year or buy a 79 EU subscription from Parleys for all
          those fantastic talks (>120) given at Devoxx this year. The slides are given below, hosted by 
          <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/roland.huss/jolokia-devoxx">Slideshare</a> and
          the <a
          href="http://labs.consol.de/blog/jolokia/devoxx-talk-jolokia-jmx-on-capsaicin-shownotes/">shownotes</a>
          with all the links are given our blog. Devoxx was definitely
          my personal highlight this year and I hope to get the chance
          to present in Antwerp next year, too.</li>
          <li>I also gave a <a
          href="http://www.netways.de/index.php?id=3031&amp;L=1">talk</a>
          at the <a
          href="http://www.netways.de/en/osmc/y2011/overview/">Open
          Source 
          Monitoring Conference 2011</a> in Nuremberg, where I was the
          'Java guy' this year. It was my thirds time at OSMC and it
          was as always a big pleasure to meet the Nagios folks and
          catering was phantastic, too ;-)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          So what's next ? There will be a minor release 1.0.2 in the
          first january week containing some minor feature additions
          and library updates. And I'm going to start the work on a
          whole new Jolokia based open source web console, called <a
          href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aj%C3%AD_pepper">Aji</a>. 
        </p>
        <p>
          Please stay tuned and a happy new year !
        </p>
<div style="width:510px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/10259713" width="510" height="426" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div>
      </subsection>
  </section>
</body>

</document>

