<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  
  <properties>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <author email="roland@jolokia.org">Roland Huss</author>
  </properties>

  <head>
    <meta name="description" content="Jolokia is an alternative to JSR-160 connectors for remote JMX access. It provides REST-like access to JMX with JSON over HTTP."/>
    <link rel="alternate" 
          type="application/rss+xml" 
          title="Jolokia" 
          href="http://labs.consol.de/tags/jolokia/feed" />
  </head>

  <body>
    <div class="teaser">
      <strong>Jolokia</strong> is remote JMX with JSON over HTTP.<br/>
      <div class="subtitle">It is fast, simple, polyglot and has unique features. 
      It's JMX on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capsaicin">Capsaicin</a>.</div>
    </div>
    <p>
      Jolokia is a JMX-HTTP bridge giving an alternative to JSR-160
      connectors.  It is an agent based approach with support for many
      platforms. In addition to basic JMX operations it enhances JMX
      remoting with unique features like bulk requests and fine grained
      security policies. 
    </p>
    <subsection name="Starting points">
      <ul>
        <li>
          Overview of <a href="features-nb.html">features</a> which
          make Jolokia unique for JMX remoting.
        </li>
        <li>          
          The <a href="documentation.html">Documentation</a> includes
          a <a href="tutorial.html">tutorial</a> and a <a
          href="reference/html/index.html">reference manual</a>.
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="agent.html">Agents</a> exist for many
          platforms (JEE, OSGi, Mule, JVM).          
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="support.html">Support</a> channels are available in both <a
          href="support.html#Your_Support_for_Jolokia">directions</a>.
          You are also welcome to add to the <a
          href="support.html#Source">evolution</a> of Jolokia.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </subsection>
    <section name="News">
      <subsection name="Happy new year 2012 !">
        <div class="news-date">2011-12-29</div>
        <p>
          The last year was very exciting for Jolokia:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>We hit 1.0.0 in October after one year of active development</li>
          <li>Jolokia was presented at <a
          href="http://www.devoxx.com">Devoxx 2011</a> in the
          "<em>Tools in action</em>" track. Despite the competition on
          the parallel tracks was very strong and some technical issues, I
          think the talk went rather well (although there is of course
          quite some space for improvement ;-). I blogged about my
          <a
          href="http://labs.consol.de/blog/devoxx/devoxx-2011-day-1/#jolokia">experience</a>
          and you can find the <a
          href="http://www.parleys.com/d/2864">full talk</a> recorded
          at Parleys. In order to see the full talk you either need to
          wait a year or buy a 79 EU subscription from Parleys for all
          those fantastic talks (>120) given at Devoxx this year. The
          <a href="">slides</a> can also be found on Slideshare and
          the <a
          href="http://labs.consol.de/blog/jolokia/devoxx-talk-jolokia-jmx-on-capsaicin-shownotes/">shownotes</a>
          with all the links are given our blog. Devoxx was definitely
          my personal highlight this year and I hope to get the chance
          to present in Antwerp next year, too.</li>
          <li>I also gave a <a
          href="http://www.netways.de/index.php?id=3031&amp;L=1">talk</a>
          at the <a
          href="http://www.netways.de/en/osmc/y2011/overview/">Open
          Source 
          Monitoring Conference 2011</a> in Nuremberg, where I was the
          'Java guy' this year. It was my thirds time at OSMC and it
          was as always a big pleasure to meet the Nagios folks and
          catering was phantastic, too ;-)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          So what's next ? There will be a minor release 1.0.2 in the
          first january week containing some minor feature additions
          and library updates. And I'm going to start the work on a
          whole new Jolokia based open source web console, called <a
          href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aj%C3%AD_pepper">Aji</a>. 
        </p>
        <p>
          Please stay tuned and a happy new year !
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="1.0.1 is out"> 
        <div class="news-date">2011-10-31</div>
       <p>
          A minor bug fix release, probably the last before Devoxx,
          brings also two new features:
          </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            The <a href="agent/jvm.html">JVM Agent</a> can now also take a regular
            expression as argument for specifying a process to attach
            to. This pattern is matched against the process'
            name. Alternatively you can of course specify the process id
            as before.
          </li>
          <li>
            Collections which are not lists or maps (like <code>Set</code>) are
            serialized properly as JSON arrays.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          Jolokia is now available also at <a
          href="http://search.maven.org/">Maven Central</a> so adding
          the <a href="http://labs.consol.de/maven/repository/">Consol
          Labs repository</a> is not required anymore in your poms
          (except you want depend on Jolokia <a
          href="http://labs.consol.de/maven/snapshots-repository/">snapshots</a>).
        </p>
        <p>
          Happy Halloween ....
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Jolokia and Jmx4Perl on tour">
        <div class="news-date">2011-08-29</div>
        <div style="margin-left: 30px; float:right">
          <a style="background: none;" href="http://www.devoxx.com"><img src="images/banner/devoxx.png" alt="Devoxx"/></a>
        </div>        
        <p>
          <em>Meet us in Paradise</em> at Devoxx 2011 ! "<a
          href="http://www.devoxx.com/display/DV11/Jolokia+-+JMX+on+Capsaicin">Jolokia
          - JMX on Capsaicin</a>" will be presented on November 14th
          2011 in Antwerp, Belgium. I'm really excited to have the
          chance to bring some chili pepper to this superb premium
          conference which I greatly enjoyed as visitor in the
          past. 30 minutes are surely not long enough for getting in
          every feature, so please le me know whether you have a
          favourite one.
        </p>
        <div style="clear: both"></div>
        <div style="margin-left: 30px; margin-top: 20px; float:right">
          <a style="background: none;" href="http://www.netways.de/en/osmc/y2011/"><img src="images/banner/osmc_2011.png" alt="OSMC 2011"/></a>
        </div>        
        <p>
          The second conference where Jolokia will play its role this
          autumn is at the Open Source Monitoring Conference "<a
          href="http://www.netways.de/en/osmc/y2011/programm/v/nagios_java_monitoring_mit_jmx4perl_und_jolokia/">Nagios
          Java monitoring with Jmx4Perl and Jolokia</a>" in Nuremberg
          on November 30th 2011. It's a quite different talk with
          focus on Jmx4Perl, discovery of relevant monitoring metrics
          and it's configuration in a Nagios environment. Not much
          Java here, but tooling en masse. I'm really looking forward
          to this home play, too.
        </p>
        <div style="clear: both;"></div>
        <p>
          If you intend to participate in one of these conferences and
          would like some discussion about Jolokia, Jmx4Perl, JMX,
          Chili pepper growing, the world, you can contact me on various
          channels. Jolokia can be found at twitter at <code><a
          href="http://twitter.com/jolokia_jmx">@jolokia_jmx</a></code>,
          the <a href="forum.html">forum</a> or on IRC at the Freenode
          channel <code>#jolokia</code>. For a simple chat you can use
          also the new <a href="irc.html">webchat</a> on this site. I
          would really like to hear from you !
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="1.0.0">
        <div class="news-date">2011-10-03</div>
        <p>
          It's time to celebrate: After two and half years of hard
          work, Jmx4Perl and Jolokia have been all wrapped up for
          their 1.0 releases.
        </p>
        <p>
          The last month the focus was on hardening this first
          official release. This effort is backed up by these numbers:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            216 integration tests which has been successfully run on
            <a href="agent.html">38</a> different platforms.
          </li>
          <li>
            a unit test coverarge of 82.7% with 404 Java and 194
            Javascript unit tests.  
          </li>
          <li>
            a <a
            href="http://docs.codehaus.org/display/SONAR/Technical+Debt+Calculation">technical
            debt</a> of 2% (or 8 man day) as measured by <a
            href="http://www.sonarsource.org">Sonar</a>
          </li>
          <li>
            other Sonar metrics inlcuding:
            <ul>
              <li>
                100% rule compliance
              </li>
              <li>
                0% package tangle index
              </li>
              <li>34.1% comments and 100% documented API</li>
              <li>94.6% total quality</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          The detailed code metrics can be examined on <a href="http://labs.consol.de/sonar/dashboard/index/org.jolokia:jolokia">Jolokia's
          Sonar Dashboard</a> and it's evolution over time is
          documented in the <a href="http://labs.consol.de/sonar/timemachine/index/946">time machine</a>
        </p>
        <p>
          I'm very confident that this 1.0.0 version is rock solid
          and production ready.
        </p>
        <p>
          There has been a minor protocol change for the way how
          Jolokia does URL escaping for slashes within GET requests,
          though. This scheme is not backwards compatible to the
          pre-1.0 protocol (which used a different, more complicated
          algorithm). Clients need to be updated, which has been
          already done for Jmx4Perl 1.00 and of course Jolokia 1.0.0's
          Javascript und Java client libraries.  Since Jolokia is out
          of beta now such kind of change won't happen in this ad-hoc
          manner in the future, promised.
        </p>
        <p>
          All changes for this release are summarized as always in the 
          <a href="changes-report.html">change log</a>. 
        </p>
      </subsection>
  </section>
</body>

</document>

