<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ Copyright 2009-2013 Roland Huss
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<chapter id="architecture">
  <title>Architecture</title>
  <para>
    The architecture of Jolokia is quite different to that of JSR-160
    connectors. One of the most striking difference is Jolokia's
    typeless approach.
  </para>
  <para>
    JSR-160, released in 2003, has a different design goal than
    Jolokia. It is a specification with which a client can transparently
    invoke MBean calls, regardless whether the MBean resides within a
    local or remote MBeanServer. This provides a good deal of
    comfort for Java clients of this API, but it is also dangerous
    <emphasis>because</emphasis> it hides the remoteness of JMX
    calls. There are several subtle issues, performance
    being one of them. It <emphasis>does</emphasis> matter whether a
    call is invoked locally or remotely. A caller should at least be
    aware what happens and what the consequences are. On the other
    side, there are message passing models which include remoting
    explicitly, so that the caller <emphasis>knows</emphasis> from
    the programming model that she is calling a potentially expensive
    remote call. This is probably the main reason why RMI (the default
    protocol stack of JSR-160 connectors) lost market share to
    more explicit remote protocols.
  </para>
  <para>
    One problem with JSR-160 is it implicit reliance on RMI and its
    requirement for a complete (Java) object serialization mechanism
    for passing management information over the wire. This closes the
    door for all environments which are not Java (or more precisely, JVM)
    aware. Jolokia uses a typeless approach, where some sort of
    lightweight serialization to JSON is used (in both directions, but
    a bit <emphasis>asymmetrically</emphasis> in its capabilities). Of course
    this approach has some drawbacks, too, but also quite some
    advantages. At least it is unique in the JMX world ;-).
  </para>

  <section id="agent-mode">
    <title>Agent mode</title>
    <para>
      <xref linkend="fig-architecture-overview"/> illustrates the
      environment in which Jolokia operates. The agent exports on the
      frontside a JSON based protocol over HTTP that gets bridged to
      invocation of local JMX MBeans. It lives outside the JSR-160
      space and hence requires a different setup. Various techniques
      are available for exporting its protocol via HTTP. The most
      prominent being to put the agent into a servlet container. This
      can be a lightweight one like Tomcat or Jetty or a full-blown
      Java EE Server. Since it acts like a usual web application the
      deployment of the agent is well understood and should pose no
      entry barrier for any developer who has ever dealt with Java web
      applications.
    </para>

    <figure id="fig-architecture-overview">
      <title>Jolokia architecture</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="architecture.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      But there are more options. Specialized agents are able to use an OSGi
      HttpService or come with an embedded Jetty-Server in case of the
      Mule agent. The JVM agent uses the HTTP-Server included
      with every Oracle JVM 6 and can be attached dynamically to any
      running Java process. Agents are described in detail in <xref
      linkend="agents"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Jolokia can be also integrated
      into one's own applications very easily. The <literal>jolokia-core</literal>
      library (which comes bundled as a jar), includes a servlet
      which can be easily added to a custom application. <xref
      linkend="agent-war-programmatic"/> contains more information
      about this.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="proxy-mode">
    <title>Proxy Mode</title>
    <para>
      Proxy mode is a solution for when it is impossible to deploy
      the Jolokia agent on the target platform. For this mode, the
      only prerequisite for accessing the target server is a JSR-160
      connection. Most of the time this happens for political reasons,
      where it is simply not allowed to deploy an extra piece of
      software or where doing so requires a lengthy approval process.
      Another reason could be that the target server already
      exports JMX via JSR-160 and you want to avoid the extra step of
      deploying the agent.
    </para>

    <para>
      A dedicated proxy servlet server is needed for hosting
      <literal>jolokia.war</literal>, which by default supports both
      the <emphasis>agent mode</emphasis> and the <emphasis>proxy
      mode</emphasis>. A lightweight container like Tomcat or Jetty is
      a perfect choice for this kind of setup.
    </para>
    <para>
      Figure <xref linkend="fig-architecture-proxy"/> describes  a typical setup for the proxy mode. A
      client sends a usual Jolokia request containing an extra section
      for specifying the target which should be queried. All routing
      information is contained in the request itself so that the proxy
      can act universally without the need of a specific
      configuration.
    </para>

    <figure id="fig-architecture-proxy">
      <title>Jolokia as JMX Proxy</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="proxy.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>


    <para>
      Having said all that, the proxy mode has some limitations which are
      listed in <xref linkend="proxy"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
      To summarize, the proxy mode should be used only when
      required. The agent servlet on its own is more powerful than the
      proxy mode since it eliminates an additional layer adding to the
      overall complexity and performance. Also, some features like
      merging of MBeanServers are not available in the proxy mode.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>