<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="mbeans">
  <title>Jolokia MBeans</title>
  <para>
    Beside bridging JMX to the HTTP/JSON world, the Jolokia agents
    also installs own MBeans which provide extra services which are
    described in this chapter.
  </para>
  <section id="mbean-config">
    <title>Configuration MBean</title>
    <para>
      This MBean, which is registered under the name <emphasis
      role="bold">jolokia:type=Config</emphasis>, allows changing
      configuration parameters. Changes are non-persistent and get
      lost after an restart of the hosting application
      server. Debugging and the history store can be configured with
      this MBean.
    </para>
    <section id="mbean-debugging">
      <title>Debugging</title>
      <para>
        Debugging can be switched on by setting the attribute
        <literal>Debug</literal>. When debugging is switched on, the
        Jolokia agent will store debug information in a ring buffer in
        memory, whose size can be tuned with the attribute
        <literal>MaxDebugEntries</literal>. The debug information can
        be fetched by the operation <literal>debugInfo</literal>. This
        debugging output will contain the JSON responses (which in
        turn contain their requests) sent to the client. Finally, the
        operation <literal>resetDebugInfo</literal> clears the debug
        history. 
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="mbean-history">
      <title>History store</title>
      <para>
        The <emphasis>history store</emphasis> can be used to remember
        attribute and return values within the agent's memory. The
        Nagios check <command>check_jmx4perl</command> for instances
        uses this feature for its delta check feature which measure
        the increase or decrease of attribute values. In order to
        switch on history tracking, two operations are provided:
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">setHistoryEntriesForOperation</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>              
            JMX operation for switching on tracking of the execution of
            JMX operations. It takes four arguments: The MBean and
            operation name, an optional target URL when the agent
            is used in proxy mode and the number of maximal
            entries to track. If the target URL is given, than
            request for this specific target are tracked,
            otherwise, if the URL is null, requests to this
            operation on the local agent are tracked.  The return
            value of calling this operations is stored in an 
            buffer with the specified length, where the oldest
            elements will shift out in case of an overflow. 
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">setHistoryEntriesForAttribute</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>              
            JMX operation for switching on tracking of an JMX
            attribute's value. It takes five arguments: The MBean
            and attribute name, an  optional path and target URL and
            the maximal number of entries to remember. As above, the
            target URL is only used for proxy requests. The path can
            be used to store only read request with the given path. 
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>
        If for a request history tracking is switched on, the JSON
        response will contain an extra field
        <constant>history</constant> which contains a list with
        historical values along with the timestamp when it was
        recorded. This format is described in detail in <xref
        linkend="history"/>.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="mbean-serverhandler">
    <title>Server Handler</title>
    <para>
      The MBean <emphasis
      role="bold">jolokia:type=ServerHandler</emphasis> has a single
      operation <methodname>mBeanServersInfo</methodname> with no
      arguments. This operation can be used to dump out the name of
      all registered MBean on all found MBeanServers. It is helpful to
      get a quick and condensed overview of the available JMX
      information. 
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>