<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="http">
    <title>Http Support</title>

    <para>Citrus is able to connect with Http services and simulate Http servers. In the next sections you will learn
    how to invoke services using Http messaging. And you will see how to accept client requests and provide proper Http 
    responses.</para>
    
    <note>
        <para>Similar to the JMS specific configuration schema, Citrus provides a customized Http configuration schema that
        is used in Spring configuration files. Simply include the http-config namespace in the configuration XML as follows.</para>
        
        <programlisting>
  &lt;beans xmlns=&quot;http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans&quot;
     xmlns:xsi=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance&quot;
     xmlns:citrus=&quot;http://www.citrusframework.org/schema/config&quot;
     xmlns:citrus-http=&quot;http://www.citrusframework.org/schema/http/config&quot;
     xsi:schemaLocation=&quot;
     http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans 
     http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans-2.5.xsd
     http://www.citrusframework.org/schema/config 
     http://www.citrusframework.org/schema/config/citrus-config.xsd
     http://www.citrusframework.org/schema/http/config 
     http://www.citrusframework.org/schema/http/config/citrus-http-config.xsd&quot;&gt;
         
      [...]
      
  &lt;/beans&gt;
        </programlisting>
        
        <para>Now you are ready to use the customized http configuration elements using the 
        citrus-http namespace prefix.</para>
    </note>
    
    <section id="http-sender">
        <title>Http message sender</title>
        
        <para>Citrus can invoke any Http service and wait for the response. After that the response goes 
        through the validation process as usual. Let us see how a message sender for Http works:</para>
        
        <programlisting>
  &lt;citrus-http:message-sender id=&quot;httpMessageSender&quot; 
                                 request-url=&quot;http://localhost:8090/test&quot; 
                                 request-method=&quot;POST&quot;
                                 reply-handler=&quot;httpResponseHandler&quot;/&gt;
  
  &lt;citrus-http:reply-message-handler id=&quot;httpResponseHandler&quot;/&gt;
        </programlisting>
        
        <para>As Http communication is always synchronous we need a reply message handler besides the http message-sender. It is not
        very surprising that the sender also needs the <emphasis>request-url</emphasis> and a <emphasis>request-method</emphasis>. The sender
        will build a Http request and send it to the Http endpoint. The Http response is then provided to the reply handler.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="http-server">
        <title>Http server</title>
        
        <para>Sending Http messages was quite easy and straight forward. Receiving Http messages is more complicated, because Citrus 
        has to provide a Http server that is listening on a port for client connections. Once a client connection 
        is accepted the Http server must also provide a proper Http response to the client. Citrus ships with an embedded Http server 
        implementation that listens on a port for client connections.</para>
        
        <programlisting>
  &lt;citrus-http:server id=&quot;simpleHttpServer&quot; 
                 port=&quot;8090&quot; 
                 uri=&quot;/test&quot; 
                 deamon=&quot;false&quot; 
                 message-handler=&quot;emptyResponseProducingMessageHandler&quot;
                 auto-start=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
                         
  &lt;bean id=&quot;emptyResponseProducingMessageHandler&quot; 
   class=&quot;com.consol.citrus.http.handler.EmptyResponseProducingMessageHandler&quot;/&gt;
        </programlisting>
        
        <para>The Http server implementation in the example will automatically startup on application loading and will listen on
        the URL <literal>'http://localhost:8090/test'</literal> for requests. What also is very important is the message handler definition.
        Once a client request was accepted the message handler is responsible for generating a proper response to the client.</para>
        
        <para>Citrus provides several message handler implementations. Let's have a look at them in the following sections.</para>
        
        <section id="http-message-handler-empty">
            <title>Empty response producing message handler</title>
            
            <para>This is the simplest message handler you can think of. It simply provides an empty success response using the Http
            response code 202. In the introducing example this message handler was used to provide response messages to the calling client.
            The handler does not need any configurations or properties as it simply responds with an empty Http response.</para>
            
            <programlisting>
  &lt;bean id=&quot;emptyResponseProducingMessageHandler&quot; 
   class=&quot;com.consol.citrus.http.handler.EmptyResponseProducingMessageHandler&quot;/&gt;
            </programlisting>
        </section>
        
        <section id="http-message-handler-static">
            <title>Static response producing message handler</title>
            
            <para>The next more complex message handler will always return a static response message</para>
            
            <programlisting>
  &lt;bean 
  class=&quot;com.consol.citrus.adapter.handler.StaticResponseProducingMessageHandler&quot;&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;messagePayload&quot;&gt;
          &lt;value&gt;
          &lt;![CDATA[
              &lt;ns0:Response 
                  xmlns:ns0=&quot;http://www.consol.de/schemas/samples/sample.xsd&quot;&gt;
                  &lt;ns0:MessageId&gt;123456789&lt;/ns0:MessageId&gt;
                  &lt;ns0:CorrelationId&gt;CORR123456789&lt;/ns0:CorrelationId&gt;
                  &lt;ns0:Text&gt;Hello User&lt;/ns0:Text&gt;
              &lt;/ns0:Response&gt;
          ]]&gt;
          &lt;/value&gt;
      &lt;/property&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;messageHeader&quot;&gt;
        &lt;map&gt;
          &lt;entry key=&quot;{http://www.consol.de/schemas/samples}ns0:Operation&quot; 
                    value=&quot;sayHelloResponse&quot;/&gt;
          &lt;entry key=&quot;{http://www.consol.de/schemas/samples}ns0:Request&quot; 
                    value=&quot;HelloRequest&quot;/&gt;
        &lt;/map&gt;
      &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;
            </programlisting>
            
            <para>The handler is configured with a static message payload and static response header values. The response to the client
            is therefore always identical.</para>
        </section>
        
        <section id="http-message-handler-xpath">
            <title>Xpath dispatching message handler</title>
            
            <para>The idea behind the xpath-dispatching-message-handler is that the incoming requests are dispatched to several
            message handlers according to an element value inside the message payload. The XPath expression will evaluate and
            call the respective message handler. The message handler mapping is done by their names inside a message handler Spring
            configuration context. The separate context is loaded in advance.</para>
            
            <programlisting>
  &lt;bean id=&quot;xpathDispatchingHandler&quot; 
    class=&quot;com.consol.citrus.http.handler.XpathDispatchingMessageHandler&quot;&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;xpathMappingExpression&quot; 
                   value=&quot;//MessageBody/Operation&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;messageHandlerContext&quot; 
                   value=&quot;message-handler-context.xml&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;
            </programlisting>
            
            <para>The handler receives a XPath mapping expression as well as a Spring ApllicationContext file resource. The message handlers
            are mapped to the different values via their names. For instance a incoming request with 
            <literal>//MessageBody/Operation = "getOrders"</literal> is handled by the message handler named "getOrders". The available message handlers
            are configured in the message-handler-context (e.g. EmptyResponseProducingMessageHandler, StaticResponseProducingMessageHandler, ...).</para>
        </section>
        
        <section id="http-message-handler-jms">
            <title>JMS connecting message handler</title>
            
            <para>The most powerful message handler is the JMS connecting message handler. Indeed this handler also provides the most 
            flexibility. This handler will forward incoming request to a JMS destination and waiting for a proper response on a reply destination. 
            A configured JMS message receiver can read this forwarded request internally over JMS and provide a proper response on the 
            reply destination.</para>
            
            <programlisting>
  &lt;bean id=&quot;jmsForwardingMessageHandler&quot; 
           class=&quot;com.consol.citrus.http.handler.JmsConnectingMessageHandler&quot;&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;destinationName&quot; value=&quot;JMS.Queue.Requests.In&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;replyDestinationName&quot; 
                   value=&quot;JMS.Queue.Response.Out&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;connectionFactory&quot;&gt;
          &lt;bean class=&quot;org.apache.activemq.ActiveMQConnectionFactory&quot;&gt;
              &lt;property name=&quot;brokerURL&quot; 
                           value=&quot;tcp://localhost:61616&quot; /&gt;
          &lt;/bean&gt;
      &lt;/property&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;replyTimeout&quot; value=&quot;2000&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;
            </programlisting>
            
            <tip>
                <para>The samples section may help you get in touch with the http configuration and the JMS forwarding stategy 
                (<xref linkend="samples"/>)</para>
            </tip>
        </section>
    </section>    
</chapter>