<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="reporting">
    <title>Reporting and test results</title>
  
    <para>The framework generates different reports and results after a test run for you. These report and result pages will
    help you to get an overview of the test cases that were executed and which one were failing.</para>
  
    <section id="reporting-logging">
        <title>Console logging</title>
    
        <para>During the test run the framework will provide a huge amount of information that is printed out to
        the console. This includes current test progress, validation results and error information. This
        enables the user to quickly supervise the test run progress. Failures in tests will be printed to the
        console just the time the error occurred. The detailed stack trace information and the detailed
        error messages are helpful to get the idea what went wrong.</para>

        <para>As the console output might be limited to a defined buffer limit, the user may not be able to
        follow the output to the very beginning of the test run. Therefore the framework additionally
        prints all information to a log file according to the logging configuration.</para>
    
        <para>The logging mechanism uses the SLF4J logging framework. SLF4J is independent of logging framework implementations on the 
        market. So in case you use Log4J logging framework the specified log file path as well as logging levels can be freely configured 
        in the respective log4j.xml file in your project. At the end of a test run the combined test results get printed to both console 
        and log file. The overall test results look like following example:</para>
        
        <programlisting>
            <literal>
  TEST RESULTS citrus-default-testsuite
  
    [...]
    HelloService_Ok_1             : successfull
    HelloService_Ok_2             : successfull
    EchoService_Ok_1              : successfull
    EchoService_Ok_2              : successfull
    EchoService_TempError_1       : successfull
    EchoService_AutomacticRetry_1 : successfull
    [...]
    
    Found 175 test cases to execute
    Skipped 0 test cases (0.0%)
    Executed 175 test cases
    Tests failed:         0 (0.0%)
    Tests successfully: 175 (100.0%)
            </literal>
        </programlisting>
        
        <para>Failed tests will be marked as failed in the result list. The framework will give a short description
        of the error cause while the detailed stack trace information can be found in the log messages
        that were made during the test run.</para>
        
        <programlisting>
  <literal>HelloService_Ok_3 : failed - Exception is Action timed out</literal>
        </programlisting>
    </section>
    
    <section id="reporting-junit">
        <title>JUnit reports</title>
    
        <para>As tests are executed as TestNG test cases, the framework will also generate JUnit compliant XML and HTML 
        reports. JUnit test reports are very popular and find support in many build management and development tools. 
        In general the Citrus test reports give you an overall picture of all tests and tell you which of them were failing.</para>
        
        <para>Build management tools like Hudson, Bamboo or CruiseControl can easily import and display the generated JUnit 
        XML results. Please have a look at the TestNG and JUnit documentation for more information about this topic as well 
        as the build management tools (Hudson, Bamboo, CruiseControl, etc.) to find out how to integrate the tests results.</para>
    </section>
    
</chapter>