<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="tibco">
    <title>TIBCO support</title>
    
    <para>The Citrus framework was designed to also connect to several TIBCO software components. The outcome is a group of
    special test actions that enable the tester to connect to the TIBCO components and execute operations towards TIBCO.</para>
    
    <section id="tibco-hawk">
        <title>Connecting with TIBCO Hawk</title>
    
        <para>TIBCO uses the enterprise monitoring tool Hawk to manage and supervise all TIBCO applications. Citrus can access Hawk
        to affect the TIBCO service instances. You can start or stop BusinessWorks process archives and process starters for instance.</para>
        
        <tip>
            <para>Use TIBCO Hawk in order to prepare the TIBCO environment according
            to the test that will be executed (unit or integration tests).</para>
        </tip>
        
        <para>The next example shows how the Hawk agent can be used in the test suite setup.</para>
        
        <programlisting>
  &lt;bean parent=&quot;tibcoHawkAgent&quot;&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;methodName&quot; 
                   value=&quot;ResumeProcessStarter&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;methodParameters&quot;&gt;
          &lt;list&gt;
              &lt;bean class=&quot;COM.TIBCO.hawk.talon.DataElement&quot;&gt;
                  &lt;constructor-arg value=&quot;ProcessDefinition&quot;/&gt;
                  &lt;constructor-arg    
                      value=&quot;Test/UnitTest/BusinessServiceTester.process&quot;/&gt;
              &lt;/bean&gt;
          &lt;/list&gt;
      &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;
        </programlisting>
        
        <para>The example shows a method call to a Hawk agent. The method is declared through the methodName
        property. In the above example the Hawk agent will resume a particular process starter. The
        methodParameters property will cause the process starter to resume.</para>
        
        <para>In general the HawkAgent has the following properties:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>microAgent -&gt; <literal>COM.TIBCO.ADAPTER.bwengine.&lt;hawk.domain&gt;.&lt;hawk.service.instance&gt;.&lt;hawk.process.archive&gt;</literal></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>hawkDomain</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>rvService (e.g. 57500)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>rvNetwork</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>rvDaemon (e.g. tcp:57500)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>The microAgentID consists of the Hawk domain, the service instance and the process archive. With the
        right setting of the domain the service and the daemon you can now use all methods offered by the
        specific MicroAgent.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="tibco-collaborator">
        <title>Connecting with TIBCO Collaborator Workflow Server</title>
        
        <para>Similar to the Hawk agent it is useful to start and stop certain workflow jobs in the TIBCO Collaborator
        Workflow Server, especially for clean up reasons. Left over workflows from previous test runs will then get
        terminated correctly.</para>
        
        <para>The test framework offers a special action implementation, in order to clean up all available workflow jobs on
        the Workflow Collaborator Server.</para>
        
        <para>The bean looks like follows:</para>
        
        <programlisting>
  &lt;bean id=&quot;cleanIcJobs&quot;
      class=&quot;com.consol.citrus.actions.CleanIcJobsBean&quot;&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;userName&quot; value=&quot;${ic.username}&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;password&quot; value=&quot;${ic.password}&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;serverName&quot; value=&quot;${ic.servername}&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;service&quot; value=&quot;${ic.tibrv.service}&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;network&quot; value=&quot;${ic.tibrv.network}&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;daemon&quot; value=&quot;${ic.tibrv.daemon}&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;queueCount&quot; value=&quot;${ic.tibrv.queue.count}&quot;/&gt;
      &lt;property name=&quot;serverDiscoveryTimeout&quot; 
                   value=&quot;${ic.tibrv.server.discovery.timeout}&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;
        </programlisting>
        
        <para>The properties of that bean do all refer to the connection credentials of the Workflow InConcert Server instance.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>